So I want to talk a little bit about seeing the world
إذن، أريد التحدث قليلا عن رؤية العالم
from a totally unique point of view,
من خلال وجهة نظر فريدة تماما،
and this world I'm going to talk about is the micro world.
وهذا العالم الذي سأتحدث عنه، هو عالم المايكرو
I've found, after doing this for many, many years,
وجدت بعد قيامي بهذا لسنوات عديدة
that there's a magical world behind reality.
أن هناك عالما سحريا خلف العالم الحقيقي
And that can be seen directly through a microscope,
ويمكن رؤيته مباشرة من خلال المجهر
and I'm going to show you some of this today.
وسأريكم اليوم بعضا من هذا العالم.
So let's start off looking at something rather not-so-small,
حسنا، لنبدأ بالنظر إلى شيء ليس بالصغير جدا
something that we can see with our naked eye,
شيء بالإمكان رؤيته بالعين المجردة
and that's a bee. So when you look at this bee,
وهذا الشيء هو النحلة، فعندما تنظر إلى هاته النحلة
it's about this size here, it's about a centimeter.
إنها بهذا الحجم، حوالي السنتيمتر
But to really see the details of the bee, and really
لكن إذا أردنا أن نرى تفاصيل هاته النحلة،
appreciate what it is, you have to look a little bit closer.
ونقدّر فعلا ماهيتها، علينا النظر أقرب قليلا
So that's just the eye of the bee with a microscope,
إذن هذه عين النحلة من خلال المجهر
and now all of a sudden you can see that the bee has
وفجأة يمكنك أن ترى أن للنحلة
thousands of individual eyes called ommatidia,
آلاف من الأعين، وتسمى الأومتـيديا
and they actually have sensory hairs in their eyes
وهو بالفعل يمتلك شعيرات استشعار في أعينه
so they know when they're right up close to something,
فيستطيع معرفة مدى قربه من شيء ما
because they can't see in stereo.
لأنه لا يستطيع رؤية التجسيم.
As we go smaller, here is a human hair.
ونحن نكبّر أكثر، هذه شعرة إنسان.
A human hair is about the smallest thing that the eye can see.
شعرة الإنسان تعتبر أصغر شيء يمكن أن تراه العين المجردة.
It's about a tenth of a millimeter.
إنها بسمك حوالي العشر ميليمترات.
And as we go smaller again,
ونحن نكبّر أكثر مجددا،
about ten times smaller than that, is a cell.
حوالي عشر مرات أصغر من ذلك، إنها خلية
So you could fit 10 human cells
يمكن أن تضع 10 خلايا بشرية
across the diameter of a human hair.
على امتداد قطر شعرة إنسان.
So when we would look at cells, this is how I really got
بحيث أنه حين ننظر إلى الخلية، هكذا صرت
involved in biology and science is by looking
متعلقا حقا بالأحياء والعلوم وذلك عن طريق النظر
at living cells in the microscope.
إلى خلية حية في المجهر.
When I first saw living cells in a microscope, I was
عندما رأيت خلية حية للمرة الأولى في المجهر،
absolutely enthralled and amazed at what they looked like.
كنت مسحورا ومندهشا تماما لما كانت تبدو عليه.
So if you look at the cell like that from the immune system,
فإذا نظرت إلى الخلية هكذا من جهاز المناعة
they're actually moving all over the place.
فهم في الحقيقة يتحركون في كل اتجاه.
This cell is looking for foreign objects,
هذه الخلية تبحث عن مكون خارجي،
bacteria, things that it can find.
دخيل أو بكتيريا، أشياء يمكن أن تجدها.
And it's looking around, and when it finds something,
وهي تبحث في الجوار، فعندما تجد شيئا،
and recognizes it being foreign,
وتتعرف عليه على أنه دخيل،
it will actually engulf it and eat it.
ستقوم فعليا بابتلاعه وأكله.
So if you look right there, it finds that little bacterium,
إذا نظرت هناك، سترى البكتيريا الصغيرة
and it engulfs it and eats it.
وقد تم أكلها وابتلاعها.
If you take some heart cells from an animal,
إذا أخذت خلايا القلب من حيوان،
and put it in a dish, they'll just sit there and beat.
ووضعتها في صحن، ستظل هناك تنبض.
That's their job. Every cell has a mission in life,
هذه هي وظيفتها، كل خلية لها مهمة في الحياة،
and these cells, the mission is
وهذه الخلايا، مهمتها هي
to move blood around our body.
تحريك الدم حول الجسد.
These next cells are nerve cells, and right now,
الخلايا التالية هي خلايا الأعصاب، والآن
as we see and understand what we're looking at,
كما نرى ونفهم ما الذي ننظر إليه،
our brains and our nerve cells are actually doing this
تقوم الآن خلايا دماغنا وأعصابنا بعمل هذا
right now. They're not just static. They're moving around
ليست ثابتة، إن الخلايا في حركة
making new connections, and that's what happens when we learn.
تصنع روابط جديدة، وهذا ما يحدث عندما نتعلم.
As you go farther down this scale here,
كلما تعمقت أكثر هنا في المقياس،
that's a micron, or a micrometer, and we go
ذلك هو الميكرون، أو الميكرومتر، ها نحن ذا
all the way down to here to a nanometer
نزولا إلى هنا إلى النانومتر
and an angstrom. Now, an angstrom is the size
والأنغستروم. الآن الأنغستروم هو بنفس مقياس
of the diameter of a hydrogen atom.
قطر ذرة الهيدروجين.
That's how small that is.
ذلك مقدار صغر ذلك.
And microscopes that we have today can actually see
والمجاهر التي نتوفر عليها اليوم، تستطيع أن ترى
individual atoms. So these are some pictures
ذرات منفردة. وهذه بعض الصور
of individual atoms. Each bump here is an individual atom.
لذرات منفردة. كل نتوءة هنا هي عبارة عن ذرة.
This is a ring of cobalt atoms.
هذه حلقة لذرات الكوبالت.
So this whole world, the nano world, this area in here
إذن فكل هذا العالم، عالم النانو، هذه المنطقة هنا
is called the nano world, and the nano world,
تسمى عالم النانو، وعالم النانو،
the whole micro world that we see,
وعالم المايكرو كله الذي نراه،
there's a nano world that is wrapped up within that, and
هناك عالم نانو مضمّن في ذلك،
the whole -- and that is the world of molecules and atoms.
وكامل - وذاك هو عالم الجزيئات و الذرات.
But I want to talk about this larger world,
لكني أريد الحديث عن هذا العالم الأوسع،
the world of the micro world.
عالم المايكرو.
So if you were a little tiny bug living in a flower,
لذا إذا كنت حشرة صغيرة تعيش في زهرة،
what would that flower look like, if the flower was this big?
كيف ستبدو تلك الزهرة، إذا كانت الزهرة بهذا الكبر؟
It wouldn't look or feel like anything that we see
لن تشبه أو تماثل أي شيء نعرفه
when we look at a flower. So if you look at this flower here,
عندما نرى زهرة. إذا نظرت إلى هاته الزهرة هنا،
and you're a little bug, if you're on that surface
وأنت حشرة صغيرة، إذا كنت على ذلك السطح
of that flower, that's what the terrain would look like.
تلك الزهرة، هكذا ستظهر الأرضية.
The petal of that flower looks like that, so the ant
تويجة الزهرة تظهر بهذا الشكل، إذن فالنملة
is kind of crawling over these objects, and if you look
تزحف حول هذه الأشياء، وإذا نظرت
a little bit closer at this stigma and the stamen here,
بقرب إلى هذا الميسم وهذه السداة هنا،
this is the style of that flower, and you notice
هذا هو أسلوب هذه الزهرة، وستلاحظ
that it's got these little -- these are like little jelly-like things
أنها تحتوي على هاته الصغيرة - التي تشبه هلاميات صغيرة
that are what are called spurs. These are nectar spurs.
و تلك يطلق عليها مهاميز. هذا رحيق مهاميز.
So this little ant that's crawling here, it's like
فهذه النملة الصغيرة، التي تزحف هنا، إنها تشبه
it's in a little Willy Wonka land.
وكأنها في أرض ويلي ونكا صغيرة.
It's like a little Disneyland for them. It's not like what we see.
كأنها ديزني لاند صغيرة خاصة بهم. إنها ليست كما نراها.
These are little bits of individual grain of pollen
هذه حبات صغيرة من اللقاح
there and there, and here is a --
هناك وهناك، وهنا -
what you see as one little yellow dot of pollen,
ما تراه عبارة عن نقطة صفراء من اللقاح،
when you look in a microscope, it's actually made
عندما ترى من المجهر، إنها في الحقيقة مصنوعة
of thousands of little grains of pollen.
من آلاف الحبات الصغيرة من اللقاح.
So this, for example, when you see bees flying around
على سبيل المثال، عندما ترى النحل يطير حول
these little plants, and they're collecting pollen,
هذه النباتات الصغيرة، وتجمع اللقاح،
those pollen grains that they're collecting, they pack
حبات اللقاح هاته التي تجمعها، يحزمها النحل
into their legs and they take it back to the hive,
في أقدامه ثم يرجعها إلى الخلية،
and that's what makes the beehive,
وهذا ما يشكل خلية النحل،
the wax in the beehive. And they're also collecting nectar,
الشمع في خلية النحل. وتجمع كذلك الرحيق،
and that's what makes the honey that we eat.
وذلك ما يشكل العسل الذي نأكله.
Here's a close-up picture, or this is actually a regular picture
ها هي صورة أقرب، أو هذه فعليا صورة عادية
of a water hyacinth, and if you had really, really good vision,
لصفير الماء، و إذا كان لديك فعلا نظر جيد جدا،
with your naked eye, you'd see it about that well.
بعينك المجردة، يمكنك أن تراها بذلك الوضوح.
There's the stamen and the pistil. But look what the stamen
هنا السداة و مدقة الزهرة. لكن أنظر إلى السداة
and the pistil look like in a microscope. That's the stamen.
والمدقة كيف تظهر في المجهر. هذه السداة
So that's thousands of little grains of pollen there,
هذه آلاف من حبات اللقاح الصغيرة،
and there's the pistil there, and these are the little things
وها هي المدقة هناك، وهذه تلك الأشياء الصغيرة
called trichomes. And that's what makes the flower give
المسماة بالترايكومز. و هذا ما يجعل الزهرة تعطي
a fragrance, and plants actually communicate
العبير، والنباتات تتواصل بالفعل
with one another through their fragrances.
فيما بينها عن طريق العبير.
I want to talk about something really ordinary,
أريد الحديث عن شيء عادي جدا،
just ordinary sand.
فقط عن رمل عادي.
I became interested in sand about 10 years ago,
أصبحت مهتما بالرمال قبل حوالي 10 سنوات،
when I first saw sand from Maui,
عندما رأيت لأول مرة رملا من "ماوي"
and in fact, this is a little bit of sand from Maui.
في الحقيقة، هذه حفنة من رمل "ماوي"
So sand is about a tenth of a millimeter in size.
حجم الرمل حوالي عُشُر ملليمتر
Each sand grain is about a tenth of a millimeter in size.
حجم كل حبة رمل هو حوالي عُشُرُ ملليمتر.
But when you look closer at this, look at what's there.
ولكن عند إلقاء نظرة أقرب على هذا، انظروا إلى ما هناك.
It's really quite amazing. You have microshells there.
شيء مدهش حقاً. لديك صدفة مجهرية هناك.
You have things like coral.
لديك أشياء مثل المرجان.
You have fragments of other shells. You have olivine.
لديك شظايا صدفات أخرى. لديك أوليفين.
You have bits of a volcano. There's a little bit
لديك قطع من بركان. هناك قليل
of a volcano there. You have tube worms.
من بركان هناك. لديك ديدان أنبوبية.
An amazing array of incredible things exist in sand.
وتوجد في الرمال مجموعة مذهلة من أشياء لا تصدق.
And the reason that is, is because in a place like this island,
والسبب في هذا، أنها في مكان مثل هذه الجزيرة،
a lot of the sand is made of biological material
الكثير من الرمل مصنوع من المواد البيولوجية
because the reefs provide a place where all these
لأن الشعاب المرجانية توفر مكاناً
microscopic animals or macroscopic animals grow,
تنمو فيه الحيوانات المجهرية أو الحيوانات العيانية،
and when they die, their shells and their teeth
وندما تموت، أصدافهم وأسنانهم
and their bones break up and they make grains of sand,
وعظامهم تكسر وتشكل حبوب الرمل،
things like coral and so forth.
أشياء مثل الشعاب المرجانية وما إلى ذلك.
So here's, for example, a picture of sand from Maui.
لدينا هنا، على سبيل المثال، صورة لرمال من ماوي.
This is from Lahaina,
وهذا من لاهاينا،
and when we're walking along a beach, we're actually
وعندما نسير على الأقدام على طول شاطئ، نحن فعلا
walking along millions of years of biological and geological history.
نمشي على امتداد ملايين السنين من التاريخ الجيولوجي والبيولوجي.
We don't realize it, but it's actually a record
نحن لا ندرك ذلك، إلا أنها في الواقع سِجل
of that entire ecology.
كامل لعلم البيئة.
So here we see, for example, a sponge spicule,
لذا هنا نرى، على سبيل المثال، إسفنج الشوكة،
two bits of coral here,
قطعتان من المرجان هنا،
that's a sea urchin spine. Really some amazing stuff.
وهنا عمود فقري لقنفذ البحر. حقاً بعض الأشياء المدهشة.
So when I first looked at this, I was -- I thought,
عندما نظرت لأول مرة لهذا، كنت - فكرت،
gee, this is like a little treasure trove here.
إنه ككنز نفيس هنا.
I couldn't believe it, and I'd go around dissecting
لم أصدق ذلك، وأود أن أحلل بعضا من
the little bits out and making photographs of them.
القطع الصغيرة وأستفيد منها وآخد بعض الصور.
Here's what most of the sand in our world looks like.
هنا ما يشبه معظم الرمال في عالمنا.
These are quartz crystals and feldspar,
هذه هي بلورات الكوارتز والفلسبار،
so most sand in the world on the mainland
لذا معظم الرمال في اليابسة في العالم
is made of quartz crystal and feldspar. It's the erosion of granite rock.
مصنوع من كريستال الكوارتز والفلسبار. وهي تآكل لصخور الغرانيت.
So mountains are built up, and they erode away by water
إذن فالجبال قد تشكلت، وتتآكل بسبب المياه
and rain and ice and so forth,
والمطر والجليد وما إلى ذلك،
and they become grains of sand.
وتتشكل لدينا حبات الرمل.
There's some sand that's really much more colorful.
وهناك بعض الرمال التي هي حقاً كثيرة الألوان.
These are sand from near the Great Lakes,
هذه رمال قرب منطقة البحيرات الكبرى،
and you can see that it's filled with minerals
ويمكنك أن ترى أنها مليئة بالمعادن
like pink garnet and green epidote, all kinds of amazing stuff,
مثل العقيق الوردي والإيبيدوت الأخضر وأشياء مذهلة،
and if you look at different sands from different places,
وإذا نظرتم إلى رمال مختلفة من أماكن مختلفة،
every single beach, every single place you look at sand,
كل شاطئ، وفي كل مكان تنظر فيه إلى الرمال،
it's different. Here's from Big Sur, like they're little jewels.
تراها مختلفة. هنا من "بيغ سور"، كأنها جواهر صغيرة.
There are places in Africa where they do the mining
وهناك أماكن في أفريقيا حيث يتم تعدين
of jewels, and you go to the sand where the rivers have
المجوهرات، تذهب إلى الرمال حيث توجد الأنهار
the sand go down to the ocean, and it's like literally looking
التي تصل إلى المحيط، والأمر يشبه حرفيا النظر
at tiny jewels through the microscope.
إلى جواهر صغيرة من خلال المجهر.
So every grain of sand is unique. Every beach is different.
ذلك أن كل حبة رمل فريدة من نوعها. و كل شاطئ يختلف عن الآخر
Every single grain is different. There are no two grains
و كل حبة تختلف عن الأخرى. لا توجد في العالم
of sand alike in the world.
حبتان متشابهتان من الرمل.
Every grain of sand is coming somewhere and going somewhere.
كل حبة رمل قادمة من مكان ما وذاهبة إلى مكان ما.
They're like a snapshot in time.
إنا مثل لقطات زمنية.
Now sand is not only on Earth, but sand is
الآن الرمل ليس فقط على الأرض، ولكن الرمل
ubiquitous throughout the universe. In fact, outer space
في كل مكان في جميع أنحاء الكون. في الواقع، فالفضاء الخارجي
is filled with sand, and that sand comes together
مليء بالرمل، والرمال يجتمع معا
to make our planets and the Moon.
ليشكل لنا الكواكب والقمر.
And you can see those in micrometeorites.
ويمكنك أن تراها في النيازك الدقيقة.
This is some micrometeorites that the Army gave me,
هذه هي بعض النيازك الدقيقة التي أعطانيها الجيش،
and they get these out of the drinking wells in the South Pole.
وقد حصلوا عليها من آبار الشرب في القطب الجنوبي.
And they're quite amazing-looking, and these are the
وتبدو مذهلة تماما، وهذه
tiny constituents that make up the world that we live in --
المكونات الصغيرة هي التي تشكل العالم الذي نعيش فيه -
the planets and the Moon.
الكواكب والقمر.
So NASA wanted me to take some pictures of Moon sand,
لذا طلبت مني ناسا التقاط بعص الصور لرمال القمر،
so they sent me sand from all the different landings
لذا أرسلوا لي الرمال من عمليات الإنزال المختلفة
of the Apollo missions that happened 40 years ago.
بعثات أبولو التي حصلت قبل 40 عاماً.
And I started taking pictures with my three-dimensional microscopes.
وبدأت في التقاط الصور باستخدام مجاهر ثلاثية الأبعاد.
This was the first picture I took. It was kind of amazing.
وكانت هذه أول صورة أخذت. وقد كانت مدهشة نوعا ما.
I thought it looked kind of a little bit like the Moon, which is sort of interesting.
اعتقدت أنه يشبه نوعا من القمر، وهو أمر جدير بالاهتمام.
Now, the way my microscopes work is, normally
الآن، طريقة عمل مجهري، عادة،
in a microscope you can see very little at one time,
في المجهر لا يمكنك أن ترى سوى القليل جداً في وقت واحد،
so what you have to do is you have to refocus the microscope,
إذن ما عليك فعله هو إعادة ضبط تركيز المجهر،
keep taking pictures, and then I have a computer program
والاستمرار في التقاط الصور، ثم من خلال برنامج في حاسوبي
that puts all those pictures together
يجمع كل تلك الصور
into one picture so you can see actually what it looks like,
في صورة واحدة حيث يمكنك أن ترى ما تبدو عليه في الواقع،
and I do that in 3D. So there, you can see,
وأنا أفعل ذلك بأبعاد ثلاثة. ها هي، يمكنكم رؤية،
is a left-eye view. There's a right-eye view.
العين اليسرى. وهناك رؤية العين اليمنى.
So sort of left-eye view, right-eye view.
لذ فهي نوعا ما نظرة العين اليسرى والعين اليمنى.
Now something's interesting here. This looks very different
الآن، هناك شيء مثير للاهتمام هنا. هذا يبدو مختلفاً جداً
than any sand on Earth that I've ever seen, and I've
عن أي رمل على الأرض قد رأيته من قبل، وقد
seen a lot of sand on Earth, believe me. (Laughter)
عاينت الكثير من الرمال على الأرض، صدقوني. (ضحك)
Look at this hole in the middle. That hole was caused
انظروا إلى هذا الثقب في الوسط. تلك الحفرة كان سببها
by a micrometeorite hitting the Moon.
نيزك دقيق ضرب القمر.
Now, the Moon has no atmosphere, so micrometeorites
الآن، القمر لا يملك غلافا جويا، وبالتالي فالنيازك الدقيقة
come in continuously, and the whole surface of the Moon
تأتي بشكل مستمر، وسطح القمر كله
is covered with powder now, because for four billion years
مغطى بمسحوق الآن، لأنه على امتداد 4 ملايير سنة
it's been bombarded by micrometeorites,
تعرض للقصف من قبل النيازك الدقيقة،
and when micrometeorites come in at about
وعندما تأتي النيازك الدقيقة بسرعة حوالي
20 to 60,000 miles an hour, they vaporize on contact.
20 إلى 60,000 ميلا في الساعة، فإنها تتبخر حين تصطدم.
And you can see here that that is --
ويمكنك أن ترى هنا أن ذلك هو -
that's sort of vaporized, and that material is holding this
والتي هي مبخّرة نوعا ما، وتلك المواد ممسكة
little clump of little sand grains together.
بمجموعات صغيرة من حبوب الرمل معا.
This is a very small grain of sand, this whole thing.
هذه حبة صغيرة جداً من الرمل، هذا الشيء كله.
And that's called a ring agglutinate.
وتلك تدعى حلقة غروية.
And many of the grains of sand on the Moon look like that,
وكثير من حبوب الرمل على سطح القمر تبدو مثل ذلك،
and you'd never find that on Earth.
ولن تجد ذلك أبدا على الأرض.
Most of the sand on the Moon,
معظم الرمال على سطح القمر،
especially -- and you know when you look at the Moon,
خاصة - تعرفون عندما تنظرون إلى القمر،
there's the dark areas and the light areas. The dark areas
أن هناك مناطق مظلمة ومناطق منيرة. المناطق المظلمة
are lava flows. They're basaltic lava flows,
عبارة عن تدفقات لحمم بركانية. تدفقات لحمم بازلتية،
and that's what this sand looks like, very similar
وهذا ما يبدو عليه هذا الرمل، مشابه جداً
to the sand that you would see in Haleakala.
للرمال التي قد ترون في هالياكالا.
Other sands, when these micrometeorites come in,
رمال أخرى، عندما تأتي هذه النيازك الدقيقة ،
they vaporize and they make these fountains,
تتبخر وتنشئ هذه النوافير،
these microscopic fountains that go up into the --
هذه النوافير المجهرية التي ترتفع إلى -
I was going to say "up into the air," but there is no air --
كنت سأقول أعلى في الهواء، ولكن لا وجود لهواء هناك -
goes sort of up, and these microscopic glass beads
يرتفع نوعا ما إلى أعلى، وهذه حبات زجاجية مجهرية
are formed instantly, and they harden, and by the time
يتم تشكيلها على الفور، و تتصلب، وبمجرد
they fall down back to the surface of the Moon,
سقوطها مجددا على سطح القمر،
they have these beautiful colored glass spherules.
ولديها هذه الكريوات الزجاجية الملونة الجميلة.
And these are actually microscopic;
وهذه مجهرية فعلا؛
you need a microscope to see these.
تحتاج مجهرا لرؤية هذه.
Now here's a grain of sand that is from the Moon,
الآن هذه حبة رمل من القمر،
and you can see that the entire
ويمكنك أن ترى أن كامل
crystal structure is still there.
البنية البلورية لا تزال هناك.
This grain of sand is probably about
هذه الحبوب من الرمل على الأرجح عمرها حوالي
three and a half or four billion years old,
3.5 أو 4 ملايير سنة،
and it's never eroded away like the way we have sand
وهي لا تتآكل أبدا بنفس الطريقة التي يتآكل بها الرمل
on Earth erodes away because of water and tumbling,
على الأرض، حيث يتآكل بسبب المياه والهبوط،
air, and so forth. All you can see is a little bit of erosion
والهواء وهكذا دواليك. كل ما يمكنك أن تراه هو القليل من التآكل
down here by the Sun, has these solar storms,
هنا بسبب الشمس، حيث هذه العواصف الشمسية،
and that's erosion by solar radiation.
وهذا تآكل بالإشعاع الشمسي.
So what I've been trying to tell you today is
ما كنت أحاول أن أقول لكم اليوم هو
things even as ordinary as a grain of sand
أنه حتى الأشياء العادية كحبة رمل
can be truly extraordinary if you look closely
يمكن أن تكون استثنائية حقاً إذا كنت تبحث عن كثب
and if you look from a different and a new point of view.
وإذا نظرتم من وجهة نظر مختلفة و جديدة.
I think that this was best put by William Blake when he said,
وأعتقد أن ويليام بليك قد عبر عن هذا بأفضل صيغة حين قال:
"To see a world in a grain of sand
"أن ترى العالم في حبة رمل
and a heaven in a wild flower,
وجنة في زهرة برية،
hold infinity in the palm of your hand,
واللانهاية في راحة يدك،
and eternity in an hour."
والأبدية في ساعة."
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)